<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Resoto by Some Engineering Blog</title>
        <link>https://resoto.com/blog</link>
        <description>Resoto by Some Engineering Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[New Name, New Website!]]></title>
            <link>https://resoto.com/blog/2022/01/25/new-name-new-website</link>
            <guid>/2022/01/25/new-name-new-website</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Resoto Logo Graffiti]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="./img/banner.png" alt="Resoto Logo Graffiti"/></p><p><strong>This past month has been quite the roller coaster for us at <a href="https://some.engineering">Some Engineering</a>.</strong> 🎢</p><p>Right before Christmas, we decided to part ways with the name &quot;Cloudkeeper.&quot; There were many reasons behind this decision, one of which was that we did not feel the product we were developing should be limited to cloud infrastructure. We were building a product that did much more than just &quot;housekeeping for your clouds.&quot;</p><p>We partnered with brand namer <a href="http://wherewords.com">Steve Cecil</a> to devise a new name. I found the process to be really special and quite fun, though <a href="http://wherewords.com">Steve</a> did require us to invest quite a bit of our time.</p><p>The process began with each member of the &quot;naming committee&quot; individually completing a sixty-question questionnaire exploring different facets of our product and brand identity. 📝</p><p>We then met for a two-hour working session, during which we were assigned homework: to review 264 potential product names born from <a href="http://wherewords.com">Steve</a>&#x27;s genius, reading and re-reading them both front-to-back and back-to-front, and (again, individually) submit a ranked list of our favorites.</p><p>All the work <a href="http://wherewords.com">Steve</a> asked of us paid off, and we ended the second working session with our new name: <strong><em>Resoto</em></strong>. ✨</p><p>Since you&#x27;ve found your way here, you presumably have also noticed that we have a new website to accompany the rebranded project!</p><p>I joined the team as a <a href="https://github.com/lloesche/valheim-server-docker/issues/423">technical writer</a> (no, your eyes are not deceiving you—I was discovered on <a href="https://github.com">GitHub</a> as a result of my open-source contributions!) and joined the <a href="https://some.engineering">Some Engineering</a> team to find a somewhat broken documentation system and pipeline.</p><p>Documentation was formatted using <a href="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/en/master/usage/restructuredtext/basics.html">reStructredText</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/lloesche">Lukas</a> told me that he &quot;<!-- -->[<!-- -->hated<!-- -->]<!-- --> editing <a href="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/en/master/usage/restructuredtext/basics.html">reStructredText</a> in <a href="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/">Sphinx</a>, so <!-- -->[<!-- -->he doesn&#x27;t<!-- -->]<!-- --> do it.&quot; 😅</p><p><strong>You know that there is a serious problem when the developers on your team don&#x27;t want to write documentation simply because it is too painful to do so.</strong></p><p><a href="https://github.com/lloesche">Lukas</a> suggested migrating our documentation to <a href="https://docusaurus.io">Docusaurus</a>. As I began poking around and reading the <a href="https://docusaurus.io/docs">Docusaurus documentation</a>, it quickly became apparent that <a href="https://docusaurus.io">Docusaurus</a> could do <em>much more</em> than just docs! 🦖</p><p>We originally intended to partner with a design firm to create a design for the Resoto website, which would also serve as the new, more appropriate home for our documentation. However, I couldn&#x27;t ship <code>resoto.com/docs</code> without <code>resoto.com</code>, so I found myself blocked.</p><p>Being a generally grumpy person when I do not have something concrete to show for my time and effort (and, perhaps also somewhat importantly, possessing some web design and frontend development experience)… I decided to take matters into my own hands.</p><p>And now, you&#x27;re looking at the result! I can attest to <a href="https://docusaurus.io">Docusaurus</a> being very easy to set up and work with, especially if you have experience with <a href="https://reactjs.org">React</a>. ⚛️</p><p>P.S.: If you are also head-over-heels in love with our sheep logo and mascot, it was created in-house by our insanely talented designer <a href="https://github.com/RPicster">Raffaele</a>. Please be on the lookout for a future blog post about the design process. 🎨</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>